Hello English learners.
Welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco
and I'm Erica and today
we're bringing you
another part of our sports
series and today we're going to be talking
about volleyball. That's right and we're
going all the way to
New Zealand to visit the
men's volleyball
championships. So we're going
to be looking at some
great words and phrases
related to volleyball
and also how to describe
a sporting event.
So before we start on
the dialogue let's take a look at
two words on vocabulary preview.
Very capillary preview.
Alright we're going to hear
both of these words
in the dialog. Now the
first one encounter encounter.
An exciting encounter.
Alright so if we have an exciting
encounter it means we
have an exciting meeting
of two people or two
teams or two groups.
If I say I had an incredible encounter last
night with my best friend. You met up your
best friend with your best
friend and something happened.
Okay so that's what an
encounter would mean.
Yes. Looking at our
second word now.
Powerhouse. Two
powerhouse teams.
Alright so we have two
powerhouse teams, China and Brazil.
That's right. So a
powerhouse team is
basically a strong,
powerful, really energetic,
great team right?
Okay so we can use it for
teams such as in this case
but we can also describe
maybe a company or a
person at a powerhouse.
That guy is a powerhouse.
He can lift 500 pounds.
Now I think it's time for us to listen
to our dialogue for the first time.
We're going to be listening
to this great sporting
event as we are taken
to New Zealand to see
China and Brazil play.
It's a beautiful day here
in New Zealand at the men's
volleyball world championship.
My name is Rick Field and I'm joined
by the man of the plant Bob Copeland.
Thank you Rick. We've got
a very exciting encounter
ahead of us today is
two powerhouse teams
Brazil and China. Face off against each
other and try to qualify for the next round.
Without a doubt both
teams are in top shape and
this will prove to be
a competitive match.
The ref signals a start of
the game and here we go.
We bear who serves and China quickly
receives the ball. Chun bumps it to the
setter and a very
nice set by Chun.
Shoe spice it. Wow what
a great hit. The Brazilian
blockers anticipated
the play and tried to
block him but he
managed to get the ball in.
Great play. It's
China service now.
What a superb jump serve by Lee.
Oh. Oh and we have a let's serve.
The ball was coming in fast and almost
made it over the net. Brazil calls for
a timeout and we'll be right back
after a short commercial break.
Well sounds like a
pretty exciting encounter
between these two countries. Very good
teams and both of them as they mentioned are
powerhouse teams. Well
why don't we take a look
at some of the vocabulary
that we came across
in this dialogue. We're
going to be focusing
on volleyball words here
in language takeaway.
Language takeaway. Okay so in language
takeaway today we're going to have six words
and let's start
with the first one.
Chin bumps it to the
setter. All right two bump.
All right so in volleyball
when you are going
to receive the ball you put your arms
together and you hit it with your four arms.
That's right so at
the top of your arm.
Right and that's how you
pass it to another player.
That's called a bump.
So it is a noun and a verb.
A bump to bump. Exactly.
Now another type of way
to move the ball in volleyball we heard in
the dialogue is a set. A very nice set by
chin. So a set or two
set? Right the word can
be used as a verb and
a noun and again you
take the ball and you
move it with the tips
of your fingers. That is
actually done by the setter.
Right that is done by the setter and
he does this, he sets the ball so then the
attacker can spike
the ball. That's our next
word, two spike. So two
spike the ball or a spike
is when you hit the ball very hard
and very fast with the palm of your hand.
That's right and that's how
you score your points right?
Exactly so you'll see
three basic moves.
The bumps set and spike.
But what about the serve?
All right so our fourth
word in volleyball is service.
So it's China's service now.
Right so the service is
the opportunity for the
team to serve the
ball. Yep pretty simple.
Right and that means
basically to start the game
by hitting it to the other side.
Now one type of serve is
the jump serve. Jump serve.
Now this is very popular
and you will see some
players do this. They
will throw the ball in the
year and then jump
in the year and hit it.
That's right. All right so
that's a jump serve and our
last word for today
is let's serve. Let serve.
Okay we have a let
serve today. So a let serve
is when you serve the ball and
it sort of brushes over the net.
Right it'll hit the net but it
will still pass to the other side.
That's right and that's an
illegal move in volleyball isn't it?
When you are serving
yes. So a let serve.
Right so those are the six
terms related to volleyball
that we're going to be
looking at today and well
with this in mind let's
move on to looking at
some phrases now in what is it?
Fluency Builder. Fluency
Builder. All right so our two
announcers Bob and
Rick said that we've got an
exciting encounter ahead
of us. Right so they use
this phrase ahead
of us ahead of us.
So basically what does that
mean? Something will happen in the
very near future. So they
are expecting it or they
will encounter it maybe.
Yes so why don't we give a
few examples of this
phrase Marco we've got a
long day ahead of us.
We have a very exciting
trip ahead of us today.
Okay so ahead of us.
So we know it's an exciting
game and we heard the
announcers say without a doubt
both teams are in top shape.
Okay so the phrase
without a doubt.
Without a doubt. So
if I start a phrase using
without a doubt. You're
basically saying there's no
question it's so obvious
this definitely is true.
It's very true. Okay so
without a doubt English
part is the best podcast
out there. Without a doubt
this is the strategy
we should take.
Okay very good so without a
doubt. Why don't we move on
to our third phrase now.
This will prove to be a
competitive match. So
let's look at the phrase
will prove to be something
will prove to be. Okay
so before we get into it why
don't we listen to some examples.
Example one. And
I think you'll prove
to be the greatest
president we've ever had.
Example two. The new
HR policy is proving to be a
waste of time. Example
three. We were worried
that we were going to
get laid off but our fears
proved to be untrue. Okay
so when something will
prove to be it will show
itself to be this thing right.
It will demonstrate.
We will see it.
We will see for sure how
it will be. And now for our
fourth phrase. A very simple
one but very common in
sports commentators or
when you're watching a game.
You'll say great play.
Great play. Great play.
Great play. Now we know
play is usually a verb right.
But here it's acting as a
noun. A play is basically
a move in a sport or a
game. So when somebody
says a great play it
means all the secession
of moves and passes
and hits to make the point.
Yep. So it was a great
play. And that you can
use that for any sport.
Right. So why don't we
listen to our dialogue
now for the second time.
And then we'll come back and talk
about this very popular sport volleyball.
It's a beautiful day here in New Zealand
at the men's volleyball world championship.
My name is Rick Field and I'm joined
by the man of the plan Bob Copeland.
Thank you Rick. We've
got a very exciting
encounter ahead of us today
is two powerhouse teams
Brazil and China face off against each
other and try to qualify for the next round.
Without a doubt both
teams are in top shape
and this will prove to
be a competitive match.
The ref signals a start of
the game and here we go.
Ribere who serves and
China quickly receives the ball.
Chun bumps it to the center
and a very nice set by Chun.
Shoe spikes it. Wow.
What a great hit.
The Brazilian blockers
anticipated the play and tried to
block him but he
managed to get the ball in.
Great play. It's China
service now. What a superb
jump serve by Lee. Oh oh
and we have a let's serve.
The ball was coming
in fast and almost made
it over the net. Brazil
calls for a timeout and
we'll be right back after
a short commercial break.
So are you a
volleyball fan Marco?
It's a very nice sport. It's
very fast and it's very hard but
it's very interesting to
get together with friends
maybe at the beach and
play some beach volleyball
or something like
that. Yeah I think that's
the best place to play
volleyball. We even have
beach volleyball up in a freezing cold
Canada. And do you have sand? Occasionally.
Alright so volleyball is a
great sport but now we
want to know what sport
you want to learn about.
We've covered soccer,
we've covered basketball,
we've covered
volleyball. So tell us what
other sports you would like to
learn vocabulary and phrases on.
That's right you can tell us this and many
more things at EnglishPod.com our website
so check it out. Right
leave your questions
and comments and
we'll see you guys there.
Thanks for downloading
and until next time goodbye.
(upbeat music)